<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>

<doc>
<title>Using BGM</title>

<para>
<ptitle>About BGM</ptitle>
    In KAG, you can play Wave-based files (compressed Wave or Ogg Vorbis), MIDI sequence data, CD-XA, or audio tracks as BGM.<r/>
    Please read <link href="Prepare"/> first.<r/>
<r/>
    In this tutorial (since it's a simple tutorial), we'll use CD-DA, so set <tt>type</tt> to <tt>"CDDA"</tt> and <tt>doubleBuffered=false</tt> in Config.tjs.<r/>
<r/>
    You might wonder "What about <tt>cdVolume</tt>? What about CD-XA?" Well, since we'll specify the CD-ROM drive directly in this method, <tt>cdVolume</tt> settings aren't necessary, and you don't need CD-XA which requires additional settings for drive letters.<r/>
<r/>
    Now, please insert an appropriate music CD into your CD-ROM drive.<r/>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Let's Try It Out</ptitle>
    We use the playbgm tag to play and the stopbgm tag to stop playback. Like this...<r/>
<bq>
[wait time=200]<r/>
*start|Start<r/>
[cm]<r/>
<b>[playbgm storage="e:3"]</b><r/>
Playing... Click to stop.[l]<r/>
<b>[stopbgm]</b><r/>
</bq>
    Here, playbgm's storage is specified as <tt>e:3</tt>. <tt>e:</tt> is the CD-ROM drive letter, so adjust it to match your system. The 3 is the track number to play.<r/>
<r/>
    While we specified <tt>e:</tt> in this tutorial, normally KAG will play the CD from the volume level specified by <tt>cdVolume</tt> in Config.tjs. If you just specify the track number without specifying a drive letter like <tt>e:</tt>, KAG will search for CD-ROM drives at the volume level specified by <tt>cdVolume</tt>.<r/>
<r/>
    Also, for non-CD-DA formats, such as MIDI sequence data, you only need to specify the filename of the file you want to play in storage.<r/>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Fade In/Fade Out</ptitle>
    To perform fade in/fade out, use the fadeinbgm and fadeoutbgm tags.<r/>
    You can specify time parameter, which determines the duration of the fade in/fade out operation.<r/>
<bq>
[wait time=200]<r/>
*start|Start<r/>
[cm]<r/>
<b>[fadeinbgm storage="e:3" time=5000]</b><r/>
Playing... Click to stop.[l]<r/>
<b>[fadeoutbgm time=5000]</b><r/>
</bq>
    Note that these tags don't wait for the fade in/fade out to complete, so you need to use the [wb] tag if you want to wait for completion.<r/>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Other BGM-Related Tags</ptitle>
    There's a tag called xchgbgm for switching BGM. Cross-fade is possible with Wave-based and MIDI formats (please refer to Config.tjs).<r/>
<r/>
    Note that plugins are required when using Wave-based formats like OggVorbis, TCWF, or Microsoft ADPCM (please refer to <link href="Prepare"/>). This is the same as with sound effects.<r/>
<r/>
<note>
    For cross-fade with MIDI formats, you need data that was "created with cross-fade in mind" (for example, two songs that don't use the same channels, etc.). However, this isn't very practical.<r/>
</note>
</para>

</doc>