<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<doc>
<title>Debugging</title>

<para>
<ptitle>Debug Support Functions</ptitle>
    Both the Kirikiri engine and KAG provide various debugging support functions.<r/>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Debug Menu</ptitle>
    Setting <tt>debugMenu.visible</tt> to true in Config.tjs will make the "Debug" menu visible. This menu contains the following items:<r/>
<dl>
<dt><kw>Reload Scenario</kw></dt>
<dd>
    Reloads the current scenario file. Execution will resume from the last "saveable label" that was passed. Note that in cases of critical bugs, reloading may not work properly.
</dd>
<dt><kw>Control</kw></dt>
<dd>
    Displays Kirikiri's "Control" panel. Can also be displayed with Shift+F1. Among the buttons available in this control panel, clicking the X mark in the red circle at the top right will terminate Kirikiri (though it may not terminate properly in cases of critical bugs).
</dd>
<dt>Console</dt>
<dd>
    Displays the console (terminal).
</dd>
</dl>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Console</ptitle>
    The console is where messages output by Kirikiri and KAG are listed and displayed. It can be shown with Shift+F4. If something isn't working properly, error messages may appear in this console.<r/>
<r/>
    The console also has an input line where you can execute arbitrary TJS expressions and check their results.<r/>
<r/>
    For example, if you want to check the contents of a variable like <tt>f.flag</tt>, enter in the console:<r/>
<bq>
f.flag<r/>
</bq>
    Press enter and the console will display something like:<r/>
<bq>
15:25:04 Console: f.flag = (int)1<r/>
</bq>
    This way you can check variable contents on the fly.<r/>
<note>
    The (int) shown before the value indicates that the value is an integer. Similarly, (real) indicates a real number, (string) indicates a string. (void) indicates that the variable is undefined or contains a void type.<r/>
</note>
<r/>
    Also, if you want to set <tt>f.flag</tt> to 0, enter:<r/>
<bq>
f.flag=0<r/>
</bq>
    Press enter and at that point f.flag will be set to 0.<r/>
<note>
    The console was called Debug Message Stream (DMS) in Kirikiri1.
</note>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Other Debug Tools</ptitle>
    The <kw>trace</kw> tag is used to output variable contents to the console.<r/>
    If the program becomes unresponsive, holding down <tt>Ctrl + Alt + F12</tt> for more than 2 seconds may force Kirikiri to terminate.<r/>
</para>

</doc>