<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<doc>

<title>Displaying Backgrounds</title>

<para>
<ptitle>Displaying Backgrounds</ptitle>
    A <kw>background</kw> is a layer displayed behind the text and foreground elements. In KAG, (by default) it loads 640x480 sized images as backgrounds.<r/>
<r/>
    First, try putting any 640x480 image in the bgimage folder. Let's say this image is called bg0.jpg. This image isn't included in KAG's LZH file, so please obtain one from somewhere (^^)<r/>
    Now, let's modify the scenario we used in <link href="Letter"/> as follows:<r/>
<bq>
<b>[image storage="bg0" page=fore layer=base]</b><r/>
[wait time=200]<r/>
*start|Start<r/>
[cm]<r/>
Hello.<r/>
</bq>
    Here we're using the <kw>image</kw> tag to load bg0.jpg into the background layer of the fore page.<r/>
    While the image tag loads the file specified in the storage parameter, you can omit the extension. KAG will search for it (^^)<r/>
<r/>
    Try running this for now.<r/>
<descimg>
<dititle>Background Displayed</dititle>
<img src="BG_Displayed.jpg"/>
</descimg>
    Now, you might be wondering what "fore page" and "background layer" mean...<r/>
<r/>
<note>
    If you specify a screen size other than 640x480 using scWidth and scHeight in Config.tjs, please use background images that match those dimensions.<r/>
</note>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>KAG's Layer Structure</ptitle>
    In KAG, all screen elements are displayed by overlaying what we call "layers" (similar to layers in Photoshop; calling them layers instead of planes is just the author's habit).<r/>
<r/>
<r/>
    For example, when the display looks like this...<r/>
<r/>
<descimg>
<dititle>Display</dititle>
<img src="Layers.jpg"/>
</descimg>
<r/>
    The layer structure looks like this:<r/>
<r/>
<descimg>
<dititle>Layer Structure</dititle>
<img src="LayersDesc.jpg"/>
</descimg>
<r/>
    In KAG, the <kw>background layer</kw> base is placed at the very bottom. In front of it are three <kw>foreground layers</kw> 0, 1, and 2. Further in front are two <kw>message layers</kw>. All foreground layers and message layer 1 are invisible in their initial state (they can be made visible using the layopt tag with visible=true. For foreground layers, they can also be made visible with the image tag).<r/>
    KAG maintains two sets of this layer structure, called the <kw>fore page</kw> fore and <kw>back page</kw> back. The fore page is displayed on screen, but the back page cannot be displayed. The back page is used temporarily for transitions (screen changes).<r/>
<r/>
    The page and layer parameters we specified in the image tag indicate the fore/back page and the base/0/1/2 layer respectively.<r/>
<r/>
<note>
    Having 3 foreground layers and 2 message layers is the default configuration in Config.tjs.<r/>
    While the number of message layers and foreground layers can be specified with numCharacterLayers and numMessageLayers in Config.tjs, they can also be changed at runtime using the laycount tag.<r/>
</note>
<note>
    While "background", "foreground", "fore", and "back" might be easy to confuse, fore in the page parameter means "display screen", not "foreground layer".<r/>
    The fore/back pages are specified with fore/back in the page parameter, foreground layers are specified with 0, 1, 2... in the layer parameter, and the background layer is specified with base.<r/>
</note>
</para>
</doc>