<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<doc>
<title>Displaying Foreground Elements</title>

<para>
<ptitle>What are Foreground Elements</ptitle>
    Foreground elements are... things displayed between the background and messages, like character poses. In KAG, you can overlay up to 3 by default (more can be displayed with customization).<r/>
<r/>
    To display foreground elements with cutout shapes of characters etc., we use either masking or color key methods. In KAG, you can display foreground elements using either masks or color keys, and for image formats like PNG, ERI, or TLG5/TLG6 that can include alpha channels or transparency in the image itself, you can use the format's native transparency method.<r/>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Using Color Keys for Foreground Elements</ptitle>
    A color key is when you fill the areas that should become transparent with a specific color, making that color transparent.<r/>
    This differs slightly between full-color images and 16-color images.<r/>
<r/>
    For full-color images, you choose an "unlikely to use" color as the <kw>transparent color</kw> (color key), and fill the areas that should be transparent with it. Common unused colors include magenta (r,g,b)=(255,0,255) or green (r,g,b)=(0,255,0).<r/>
    What if you need to display actual magenta or green? In KAG, you can use colors like (r,g,b)=(254,0,255) or (r,g,b)=(0,254,0) and they'll be treated as different colors.<r/>
<r/>
    For 256-color or 16-color images, a specific <kw>palette index</kw> is used as the "transparent color". Areas filled with this palette index become transparent.<r/>
<r/>
<note>
    For image formats like PNG, there are software tools that can specify <kw>transparent colors</kw> (color keys) when saving, and you can use PNG images output by such software.
</note>
<r/>
<descimg>
<dititle>Example of Transparent Color</dititle>
<img src="ButtonGlyphImageList.png"/>
</descimg>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Using Masks for Foreground Elements</ptitle>
    In KAG, you can display foreground elements using a separate mask image to cut out the foreground image.<r/>
<r/>
    A <kw>mask image</kw> is a 256-level grayscale image of the same size as the foreground image, where the brightness directly represents "transparency". That is, brightness 0 means "completely opaque" and brightness 255 means "completely transparent". Around 128 means "half transparent". It becomes an image where the areas you want to display are dark, and areas you want transparent are light.<r/>
    Mask images must be saved in 256-level grayscale (256-color image). They won't display correctly if saved in full-color or 16-color.<r/>
    While mask images maintain transparency information, foreground images maintain color information. In this case, the foreground image is called the <kw>main image</kw>.<r/>
<note>
    For PNG, ERI, and TLG5/TLG6 format images, the PNG/ERI/TLG5 file itself can include an <kw>alpha channel</kw> (equivalent to a mask image).<r/>
    If you have software that can output such images (like GIMP for PNG), you don't need to prepare separate mask files. Also, you can easily convert between these image formats using the image format converter included with the Kirikiri SDK.</note>
<r/>
    Mask images are saved with _m added to the main image filename. For example, if the main image is hogehoge.png, its mask image would be hogehoge_m.png. This method of having separate main and mask images is called the main/mask pair format.<r/>
<r/>
    The advantage of using mask images is that you can freely specify transparency when overlaying foregrounds, and with properly created mask and main images, you can achieve nice anti-aliased edges when overlaying.<r/>
<descimg>
<dititle>Mask Example (Left: Main, Right: Mask)</dititle>
<img src="ayari.png"/>
<img src="ayari_m.png"/>
</descimg>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Let's Display Foreground Elements</ptitle>
    Now, let's prepare appropriate images according to this (please prepare images yourself...). First, here's how to display foreground elements using color keys...<r/>
<bq>
[image storage="bg0" page=fore layer=base]<r/>
[wait time=200]<r/>
*start|Start<r/>
[cm]<r/>
<b>[image layer=0 page=fore storage="as" visible=true key=0xff00ff left=340 top=100]</b><r/>
Hello.<r/>
</bq>
    The highlighted part is where we're displaying the foreground image. The <kw>image</kw> tag appeared in <link href="DispBase"/>. It's a tag for loading images. Setting layer to 0 specifies foreground layer 0.<r/>
    Here we have a key parameter. The key parameter specifies the transparent color. Specifying the transparent color in 0xRRGGBB hexadecimal format makes areas filled with color RR(red) GG(green) BB(blue) transparent. For example, key=0xff00ff makes areas colored (r,g,b)=(255,0,255) or magenta transparent. Also, specifying key=255 makes palette index 255 the color key. Please refer to <link href="Tags"/> for details.<r/>
<r/>
    storage="as" specifies to load an image named "as". The extension can be omitted. In this case, it will automatically search for and load any readable image file named "as".<r/>
<r/>
    visible=true is necessary because KAG's foreground layers are all invisible by default, so they won't display unless set to visible.<r/>
<r/>
    left=340 top=100 specify the left and top position of the foreground layer. You can specify the display position of foreground layers when loading them with the image tag.<r/>
<note>
    Display offset specification in PNG images is ignored.
</note>
<r/>
    When using mask images, the specification looks like this:<r/>
<bq>
[image storage="bg0" page=fore layer=base]<r/>
[wait time=200]<r/>
*start|Start<r/>
[cm]<r/>
<b>[image layer=0 page=fore storage="asm" visible=true left=340 top=100]</b><r/>
Hello.<r/>
</bq>
    Notice there's no key parameter.<r/>
    In this example, it will load an image named asm_m as the mask image and asm as the main image.<r/>
<r/>
    For image formats like PNG that can include alpha channels or color keys in the image itself, you don't need to specify the key parameter as in the above examples.<r/>
<descimg>
<dititle>Running Result</dititle>
<img src="LayerDisplayed.jpg"/>
</descimg>
</para>
</doc>