<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<doc>

<title>About Image Formats</title>

<para>
<ptitle>Characteristics of Each Image Format</ptitle>
    While Kirikiri/KAG can use various image formats, each has its characteristics.<r/>
<dl>
<dt><kw>BMP Images</kw></dt>
<dd>
    Kirikiri only supports uncompressed BMP. BMPs used in Kirikiri cannot use RLE compression, and even when trying to compress them during distribution, they won't compress well, so while they take up a lot of space, they load quickly.
</dd>
<dt><kw>JPEG Images</kw></dt>
<dd>
    JPEG uses (generally) lossy compression. Because of this, once compressed, the image cannot be perfectly restored to its original state. Visually, this causes image sharpness to decrease and noise appears around high-contrast edges. However, compression rates are good, and with natural images like photographs and scenery, the compression artifacts are barely noticeable, making it suitable for background images. It's not very suitable for foreground image storage (though if saving mask images in JPEG, use grayscale).
</dd>

<dt><kw>Portable Network Graphics Images</kw> (<kw>PNG Images</kw>)</dt>
<dd>
    Unlike JPEG, it uses lossless compression. While compression doesn't reduce data size as much as JPEG, image quality isn't degraded by compression. Suitable for CG. Can include alpha channel (transparency) information in the image itself.<r/>
    Also, PNG compression is recommended for mask images used in layer transitions<comlink href="Trans.html"/>.
</dd>

<dt><kw>Entis Rasterized Image format Images</kw> (<kw>ERI Images</kw>)</dt>
<dd>
    Mainly for full-color images, achieves high compression rates (about 5-7 times smaller than PNG) while being lossless, and offers relatively fast decompression. Can include alpha channel (transparency) information in the image itself.
</dd>

<dt><kw>TLG5 Images</kw></dt>
<dd>
    TLG5 images use the extension .tlg (not .tlg5). In some places, it might simply be called TLG.<r/>
    Only supports full-color images. Uses lossless compression. Can include alpha channel (transparency) information in the image itself.<r/>
    While compression isn't that high, resulting in file sizes about 3 times larger than PNG, it has the advantage of fast decompression. Can decompress images about 4-5 times faster than PNG.
</dd>

<dt><kw>TLG6 Images</kw></dt>
<dd>
    TLG6 images use the same .tlg extension as TLG5 (not .tlg6). This image format became available from Kirikiri2 Version 2.21 beta 3, featuring high compression and fast decompression speeds. Sizes are about 1-4 times smaller than PNG, with decompression speeds more than 2 times faster than PNG. While it can't handle grayscale or palette images like PNG, it can be used as an alternative to PNG for full-color images and full-color images with alpha channels.<r/>
    Only supports full-color images. Uses lossless compression. Can include alpha channel (transparency) information in the image itself.<r/>
</dd>

</dl>
<r/>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Comparison of Image Formats</ptitle>
<dl>
<dt>Decompression Speed</dt>
<dd>
    Comparing decompression speeds of each format, from fastest to slowest:<r/>
<r/>
    (Fast)    BMP > TLG5 > JPEG > TLG6 > ERI > PNG     (Slow)<r/>
<r/>
    Note that while BMP is classified as "compressed" by default in Releaser, if left uncompressed its decompression speed becomes about the same as ERI. If speed is important, it might be better to set it as "uncompressed" in Releaser.<r/>
    However, BMP files become very large. While modern PC hard disks might not be too stressed by loading, be careful as file size can significantly affect loading speed from older HDDs or CD-ROMs.
</dd>

<dt>Size</dt>
<dd>
    Comparing compressed sizes of each format (though this varies depending on the image and compression settings):<r/>
<r/>
    (Large)    BMP > TLG5 > PNG > ERI > TLG6 > JPEG     (Small)
</dd>

<dt>Quality</dt>
<dd>
    Since only JPEG uses lossy compression while all others are lossless:<r/>
<r/>
    (High)    BMP = PNG = ERI = TLG5 = TLG6  > JPEG     (Low)
</dd>
</dl>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Format Selection by Usage</ptitle>
<dl>
<dt>Background Images</dt>
<dd>
    If file size isn't a concern, BMP is fine, and quality degradation won't be an issue.<r/>
    TLG5 is also good, with manageable file sizes, no quality loss, and relatively fast decompression.<r/>
    If you're concerned about file size but want to maintain quality, TLG6, ERI, or PNG are good choices.<r/>
    If file size is a major concern and some quality degradation is acceptable, JPEG is suitable.
</dd>

<dt>Foreground Images (Character Graphics)</dt>
<dd>
    The same considerations as background images apply.<r/>
    However, JPEG cannot handle transparency in a single file, so you'll need to use the main/mask pair format.
</dd>

<dt>Images in Dynamic Scenes</dt>
<dd>
    For dynamic scenes with many visual variations, using BMP might be good for its fast decompression speed (though be mindful of file size and loading time as mentioned above).<r/>
    Since BMP files are large, compressing with TLG5 might be a good option. TLG5's fast decompression makes it suitable for such uses.<r/>
    If quality isn't a major concern, JPEG is a good choice! JPEG decompression is faster than expected, taking less than half the time of ERI or PNG. Also, quality degradation probably won't be noticeable in dynamic displays.
</dd>
</dl>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Using Alpha Channels</ptitle>
    Kirikiri can handle images with alpha channels (transparency) as foreground images. Unlike transparency using color keys, this allows for states between completely transparent and completely opaque.<r/>
    Using alpha channels enables smooth blending of edges between transparent and opaque areas, allowing partial transparency within the image.<r/>
<r/>
<descimg>
<dititle>Color Key Transparency vs Alpha Channel Transparency</dititle>
<img src="kiri_a.png"/><img src="kiri_aa.png"/>
</descimg>
    Left shows color key transparency, right shows alpha channel transparency.<r/>
    You can see the difference in edge quality when magnified. Also, the right image shows how Japanese text can be made semi-transparent.<r/>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Image Format Converter</ptitle>
    Using the image format converter (krkrtpc.exe) included with the Kirikiri SDK, you can easily convert between image formats. It can accept Photoshop data (PSD) as input. This makes it easy to create foreground images for Kirikiri from Photoshop data. You can also use this tool to convert to Kirikiri's own compression formats TLG5/TLG6.<r/>
    For details, please refer to the Kirikiri SDK help.<r/>
<note>
    The current version does not support ERI input/output.<r/>
</note>
</para>

</doc>