<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>

<doc>
<title>About History Records</title>

<para>
<ptitle>History Records</ptitle>
    History records is a feature that performs auto-saves at certain points to allow users to return to previous screens by selecting "System - Go Back".<r/>
<r/>
    To perform history recording, you need to either use the record tag or set <tt>recordHistoryOfStore</tt> in Config.tjs.<r/>
<r/>
    The "System - Go Back" menu is hidden by default, but can be shown by setting <tt>goBackMenuItem.visible</tt> to true in Config.tjs.<r/>
<r/>
    While you can go back as far as you want when selecting "System - Go Back", the number of history points can be specified with <tt>maxHistoryOfStore</tt> in Config.tjs. Be careful as allowing too many backtrack points can bloat save data. History records are saved separately for each label.<r/>
<r/>
    Note that this is a different feature from the "Label History" setting in Config.tjs.<r/>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>History Recording Timing</ptitle>
    Using the record tag allows you to record the state at that point in history. Also, depending on the <tt>recordHistoryOfStore</tt> setting in Config.tjs, history recording can be performed automatically.<r/>
    However, history isn't necessarily recorded exactly at the point where the record tag appears or at the timing specified by <tt>recordHistoryOfStore</tt>. Records are created when passing through "saveable labels" (this is when you can go back using "System - Go Back"). What's recorded is the state at the point when the previous "saveable label" was passed, so selecting "System - Go Back" will return to that position.<r/>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>record Tag Placement</ptitle>
    For simple scenarios, setting <tt>recordHistoryOfStore</tt> for automatic history recording is easier, but for complex scenarios, it might be better to manually specify history recording positions using the record tag rather than relying on automatic recording.<r/>
<r/>
    For example, if you perform history recording at choice display screens, users can return to previous choice positions by selecting "System - Go Back".<r/>
<r/>
    In this case, it's OK to place the record tag just before the [s] tag that stops at choices. Manual history recording is particularly easy to understand in screens like this where choices are made.<r/>
<r/>
    Even if a user selects "System - Go Back", they won't return exactly to where the record tag was placed. They'll return to the position of the "saveable label" that came before the record tag.<r/>
<r/>
    Note that if there are no l, p, or s tags between one "saveable label" and the next, history recording won't occur even if a record tag is written. This is because "System - Go Back" can only be selected when stopped at l, p, or s tags, so performing history recording at a location without these tags would make it impossible to return there.<r/>
</para>

</doc>