<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<doc>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
<ptitle>Introduction</ptitle>
    KAG stands for Kirikiri Adventure Game. It's a scripting system for creating adventure games and visual novels using Kirikiri.<r/>
    While KAG itself is written in Kirikiri's TJS<small>(2)</small> scripting language, KAG scenario files are text files containing "tags" (commands).<r/>
    Scenario files are edited using a text editor. You don't need to know much programming. For example, if you can write HTML in a text editor, you should find this easy to learn.<r/>
<r/>
    While you can create things using only the standard provided tags, since KAG itself is written in TJS script, you can extend functionality by either writing additional TJS scripts or directly controlling Kirikiri from within scenario files. This is one of Kirikiri/KAG's major advantages.<r/>
<r/>
<note>
    KAG 3 and later versions require Kirikiri2. Kirikiri2 is almost a complete rewrite of Kirikiri1, and KAG 3 is the new KAG written for it. While KAG 3 maintains scenario-level compatibility with previous KAG versions, there are some considerations when connecting to pre-KAG 3 projects. Please see <link href="PortFromOldKAG"/> for details.<r/>
</note>
<r/>
<note>
    The Kirikiri engine can interpret TJS scripts. KAG, which is written in TJS script, can in turn interpret KAG scenario files. Therefore, in this document, we'll use "KAG" when referring specifically to KAG, "Kirikiri" when referring to the Kirikiri engine itself, and "Kirikiri/KAG" when referring to both.<r/>
    Also, to distinguish between TJS scripts and KAG scenarios, we'll use "script" or "script file" when referring to TJS scripts, and "scenario" or "scenario file" when referring to KAG scenarios.
</note>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>What Kind of Games Can Be Made</ptitle>
    Since KAG is primarily a script for creating adventure games, you can create adventure games (naturally).<r/>
    While there are various types of adventure games, with KAG you can create adventure games where text is displayed and the story branches based on choices set within the text.<r/>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Copyright of This Document</ptitle>
    The text and most images in this document are copyrighted by W.Dee. While personal use is permitted, since some images in this document contain other people's works, please contact W.Dee if you want to redistribute either the images alone or content including the images.<r/>
<r/>
Support and downloads are available at the following page<r/>
Kirikiri/KAG Download Page: <at target="_top" href="http://kikyou.info/tvp/">http://kikyou.info/tvp/</at><r/>
</para>

</doc>