<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<doc>

<title>Using Macros</title>

<para>
<ptitle>What are Macros</ptitle>
    A macro is a way to "make certain tags and text appear as if they were a different tag".<r/>
<r/>
    It's a method to freely define new tags by combining existing tags and text.<r/>
    In KAG, you might have thought there were many screens that required specifying similar tags repeatedly, but using macros can greatly reduce such work.<r/>
    Let's make those repeated tag combinations easier with macros<tt>(^^)</tt><r/>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Basic Usage</ptitle>
    To use macros, you first need to "define" them. Once a macro is defined, you can use that macro name anywhere afterward. Therefore, it's good to write macro definitions at the beginning of first.ks or similar.<r/>
<r/>
    When defining a macro, enclose what you want the macro to do between the <kw>macro</kw> tag and <kw>endmacro</kw> tag. Specify the macro name in the name parameter of the macro tag.<r/>
<r/>
<bq>
[wait time=200]<r/>
*start|Start<r/>
[cm]<r/>
; -- Macro Definition --<r/>
<b>[macro name=newtag]</b>[font color=0xff0000]Macro will be placed here[resetfont]<b>[endmacro]</b><r/>
</bq>
<r/>
When using this, use the macro name just like a tag:<r/>
<bq>
; -- Using the Macro --<r/>
[newtag]<r/>
</bq>
<r/>
    When this runs, at the point where <tt>[newtag]</tt> appears, the tag <tt>[newtag]</tt> is replaced with <tt>[font color=0xff0000]Macro will be placed here[resetfont]</tt>, so "Macro will be placed here" will be displayed in red.<r/>
<r/>
    You can also write it across multiple lines.<r/>
<r/>
[Multiple line example omitted for brevity]
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Macro Parameters</ptitle>
    You can pass parameters to macros and have them replace parts of the macro content.<r/>
    In the macro definition, specifying values that start with <kw>%</kw> will have them replaced with parameters passed to the macro.<r/>
    Look at the following example:<r/>
<bq>
[wait time=200]<r/>
*start|Start<r/>
[cm]<r/>
; -- Macro Definition --<r/>
[macro name=newtag]<r/>
[font color=<b>%iro</b>]<r/>
Macro will be placed here<r/>
[resetfont]<r/>
[endmacro]<r/>
</bq>
<bq>
; -- Using the Macro --<r/>
[newtag <b>iro=0x00ff00</b>]<r/>
</bq>
<r/>
    In this example, the parameter named iro is replacing the color parameter of the font tag in the entity.<r/>
    When run, "Macro will be placed here" will be displayed in green.<r/>
<r/>
<r/>
    Also, specifying <kw>*</kw> for a tag's parameters in the macro will pass all parameters given to the macro. For example, if you want to make a macro combining the trans tag and wt tag:<r/>
<r/>
<bq>
[macro name=transwait][trans <b>*</b>][wt][endmacro]<r/>
</bq>
<r/>
    Writing it this way means that when using the transwait macro, all parameters specified for the transwait macro will be passed directly to the trans tag, which is useful when making macros for tags that take various parameters.<r/>
<r/>
    Macros in macros are expanded recursively, so be careful not to include your own macro inside itself(^^)<r/>
<r/>
    When a parameter might be omitted, you can specify default values by adding <kw>|</kw> (vertical bar) after the % parameter, followed by the value to use when omitted. Look at this example:<r/>
<r/>
[Example with default values omitted for brevity]
<r/>
<note>
    Please use half-width characters for parameter specifications. Full-width characters won't work properly.
</note>
</para>
</doc>