<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<doc>
<title>Common Mistakes</title>

<para>
<ptitle>Common Mistakes</ptitle>
Here are some points where mistakes and errors commonly occur.<r/>
<r/>
<dl>
<dt>Is skipping working properly?</dt>
<dd>
KAG enters skip mode through clicking "Proceed until next choice" or holding Space/Enter keys. At this time, if skip functionality isn't disabled during time-limited choices, it may cause timeouts (to handle this, use @cancelskip or @clickskip enabled=false before the time-limited choice, and @clickskip enabled=true after it ends). Also, consider the interaction between skipping and staff roll or movie scenes.<r/>
"Auto-read" might not work as expected when using simple click waits or p tags. To forcibly cancel auto-read mode, use the cancelautomode tag.<r/>
<r/>
Also, without the wt tag corresponding to the trans tag, <b>problems may occur if there's no "tag that performs processing during transition" and corresponding "wait tag"</b>. While there's usually no problem if properly structured in macros, special attention is needed when combining "tags that perform processing during transition" in ways that might overlap.
</dd>
<dt>Is loading working properly?</dt>
<dd>
KAG's save and load system has quirks - when loading, while message layer content can be restored, execution resumes after all message layers are cleared. Also, it starts with transitions, BGM, and sound effects all stopped. Everything restarts from "saveable labels", so <b>make sure there are tags that clear message layers like cm or ct within saveable labels (or ensure all message layers are cleared when starting from saveable label positions)</b>, and <b>check whether transitions are complete and fade-outs are finished at saveable labels</b>.
</dd>
<dt>Are states being preserved?</dt>
<dd>
For example, when entering CG mode and modifying message layer states for CG mode, these states must be restored when exiting CG mode.
</dd>
<dt>Is message history OK?</dt>
<dd>
It's good practice to verify what text is being displayed in the message history.
</dd>
<dt>Are waits behaving differently depending on machine specs?</dt>
<dd>
wait, without specifying mode, simply waits for the time specified by the time parameter. However, if you try to display something every second like:<r/>
<bq>
@wait time=1000<r/>
@display something<r/>
@wait time=1000<r/>
@display something<r/>
@wait time=1000<r/>
@display something<r/>
</bq>
Even if specified this way, <b>it won't exactly be every second</b>. While wait itself waits for 1 second, it doesn't account for the time taken by "display something".<r/>
Therefore, to make this exactly one second intervals, use the resetwait tag with wait mode=until like:<r/>
<bq>
@resetwait<r/>
@wait mode=until time=1000<r/>
@display something<r/>
@wait mode=until time=2000<r/>
@display something<r/>
@wait mode=until time=3000<r/>
@display something<r/>
</bq>
This waits for specified times from the point set by resetwait using wait mode=until.
</dd>
</dl>
</para>

</doc>