<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>

<doc>
<title>Implementing Save/Load Support</title>

<para>
<ptitle>KAG "Save Points"</ptitle>
In KAG, game save/load is based on what are called "save points". (This terminology is used if MainWindow.tjs hasn't been modified).<r/>
<r/>
For information about save data, please refer to <link href="SaveData"/>.<r/>
<r/>
Unfortunately, saving and loading in KAG cannot be done at any arbitrary point. You must have a <kw>saveable label</kw> as a unit, requiring specific "locations" for save/load.<r/>
<r/>
However, saving and loading is mostly done through the menu's "Save Game" and "Load Game" options, and when saving, it saves at the most recently passed "save point".<r/>
This means that even if a player saves at a point far from a "location", when loading they will start from the position of the last "location" they passed.<r/>
<r/>
These save points are labels. However, labels that serve as save points need some special formatting.<r/>
<r/>
Consider the following example:<r/>
<r/>
<bq>
[wait time=20]<r/>
<b>*start|Start</b><r/>
[cm]<r/>
This is the start[l][r]<r/>
<r/>
<b>*label2|Save Point 2</b><r/>
[cm]<r/>
This is save point 2[l][r]<r/>
<r/>
<b>*label3|Save Point 3</b><r/>
[cm]<r/>
This is save point 3[l][r]<r/>
[jump target=*start]<r/>
</bq>
<r/>
As shown, specify a | (vertical bar) after the label, followed by what will be the save point's name as a <kw>title</kw>. Titles can be duplicated. Titles appear in the "Save Game" menu items, so they should be user-friendly names. They also become the default filename in free save mode.<r/>
When jumping to a label with jump tags etc, don't specify anything after the |. In the above example we used [jump target=*start], but when specifying labels in target parameters etc, you must omit everything after |.<r/>
<r/>
Titles can be omitted like this:<r/>
<bq>
*label|<r/>
</bq>
In this case, it uses the title from the previously passed point.<r/>
<r/>
Also, putting & after | allows using variable contents as titles. For example:<r/>
<bq>
*label|&f.title<r/>
</bq>
This will use the contents of variable f.title as the title.<r/>
<r/>
Label names (text before |) must not be duplicated within the same scenario file (duplicates are OK across different scenario files). Titles are handled dynamically so the scenario writer doesn't need to worry about duplicates.<r/>
Also, these kinds of labels must always be followed by [cm].<r/>
<note>
[ct] can be used instead of [cm]. The difference is that ct sets the target message layer's visible page to message0, while cm just clears all message layers without changing the target message layer.<r/>
The reason such message layer clearing tags are needed is because <b>what's written in the message layer is not saved in save data</b>.<r/>
Also, it's recommended not to write anything between transition tags like trans and waiting tags like wt at saveable labels.
</note>
<r/>
Also, saves cannot be made at normal labels written without |.<r/>
<r/>
That's about all you need to note <tt>(^^)</tt><r/>
<r/>
The more save point labels you add, the more save opportunities you give users. Labels can be added freely - they don't necessarily need jump tags right after them.<r/>
However, please remember that these labels must always be followed by [cm].<r/>
<note>
Internally, when KAG passes a | marked (saveable) label, it temporarily saves the state at that point. When a user chooses to save, that data is what gets saved.
</note>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Using the disablestore Tag</ptitle>
The <kw>disablestore</kw> tag temporarily disables the "Save Game" function.<r/>
Saveable labels aren't needed before the main game, like in the main menu, since saving there would be meaningless.<r/>
KAG's "Save Game" function cannot be used until passing a saveable label after startup.<r/>
So while you don't need saveable labels before the main game, if you return to the main menu after ending the game, you could save from the main menu because you've already passed a saveable label.<r/>
To prevent this, write <tt>[disablestore]</tt> in places like the main menu to disable the "Save Game" function, in addition to not having saveable labels before the main game.<r/>
After writing <tt>[disablestore]</tt>, the "Save Game" function becomes unusable until passing a saveable label, just like at KAG startup.<r/>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Using the startanchor Tag</ptitle>
The <kw>startanchor</kw> tag enables the "Return to Start" menu option.<r/>
KAG's menu bar includes "System|Return to Start...".<r/>
This menu item cannot be selected by default.<r/>
To specify where to return to, write the <tt>[startanchor]</tt> tag at the location you want to return to when "Return to Start" is selected. Write this tag after saveable labels. After <tt>[startanchor]</tt>, the "Return to Start" menu becomes usable.<r/>
Also, to disable the "Return to Start" function in places like the main menu, write <tt>[startanchor enabled=false]</tt>. In this case, the "Return to Start" function becomes unusable until passing another <tt>[startanchor]</tt> tag.<r/>
<r/>
While "Return to Start" loads the save from where the startanchor tag was written, all game variables <comlink href="Var"/> are preserved (maintained).<r/>
</para>

<para>
<ptitle>Duplicate Label Handling</ptitle>
When the same label name (text before |) exists in the same scenario file, the first label remains as-is, but subsequent labels automatically get numbered as <tt>:2</tt>, <tt>:3</tt>, etc.<r/>
For example:<r/>
<r/>
<bq>
<b>*start|Start</b><r/>
<b>*start|Save Point 2</b><r/>
<b>*start|Save Point 3</b><r/>
</bq>
<r/>
The first *start remains "<tt>*start</tt>", but when jumping to subsequent *start labels, you need to use "<tt>*start:2</tt>" in target parameters etc. The third one is "<tt>*start:3</tt>".<r/>
<r/>
Also, if you omit label names, they're treated as having the same name as the previous label and get numbered.
For example:<r/>
<r/>
<bq>
<b>*start|Start</b><r/>
<b>*|Save Point 2</b><r/>
<b>*|Save Point 3</b><r/>
</bq>
<r/>
The second label becomes "<tt>*start:2</tt>". The third label becomes "<tt>*start:3</tt>".<r/>
<r/>
If both label and title are omitted, it looks like this:<r/>
<r/>
<bq>
<b>*start|Start</b><r/>
<b>*|</b><r/>
<b>*|</b><r/>
</bq>
<r/>
While this notation is convenient when you want to create saveable points without specifying different label names each time, since labels are managed by sequence numbers, if you edit the scenario file to add or remove labels in between, saves might not return to the correct position when loaded, or return tags might not return to the correct position.<r/>
<r/>
<note>
When omitting titles, it uses the title from the previously passed saveable label, but when omitting label names, it uses the previous label name in the scenario file regardless of whether that label was passed or not.<r/>
</note>

</para>

</doc>